[Music]
please um be careful this is only a one
dimensional picture
[Music]
and in higher
Dimensions it's slightly
different so I shall put that as the
warning please be careful
that we will
[Music]
see that in higher dimensions in general
dimensions a source always has index one
+
one plus
one
whereas a
Sync has
index not always necessarily minus one
but the index of the S turns out to be
minus1 to the power dimension of the
manifold so in dimension one is minus
one but in dimension two sync also has
index + one so you might wonder well
what has index minus one the answer is a
SLE but we shall come back to that in a
moment
okay let's then prove this
formula this computational formula which
says that if you are given a vector
field as a formula like this explicitly
we can calculate the index by Brute
Force just by doing a calculation as the
sign of determinant of the yoban of that
thing why is that true what we have to
prove is that the result of this
calculation agrees with our earlier um
definition the index that is the
definition of plus or minus one
depending on where that the joint
distrib joint uh joint um orientation of
gamma 0 and Gamma V matches or
mismatches the ambient orientation of M
okay in order to prove this therefore we
have to remember this whole discussion
about joint orientation and match and
mismatch it's a good time for us to
revise if you have notes in front of you
the proof of formula 8 from the previous
chapter in fact the proof goes exactly
along the same line which shows that
there are only very few main ideas in
this subject as with any subject in
mathematics and we keep using the same
ideas and we make a lot of
progress
okay here's a proof of the formula
number eight the proof is not all that
important for the remainder of this week
except as maybe a view of linear
algebra so if you getting a little
exhausted you might as well fall asleep
I'll wake you up later
on so let's say that
m is
oriented by some basis
vector by a
local
um basis of tangent vectors
E1 through e m let's say the proof of
formula 8 in the previous chapter
started exactly the same way and we
shall as we did then write this Matrix
maybe you remember that you get by
putting together all those column
vectors as e so e is an M by m
Matrix okay this is just for shortening
theal calculation it's not a new
mathematical
idea
then the orientations of
various objects are given as
follows you see in order to discuss the
index of the equilibria we have to worry
about orientation of the zero section so
going that way that's the white one and
the graph orientational graph which is
going that way or that way or that way
that's the
sort of orange one and then finally The
Joint orientation of the ambient space
of the tangent bundle which is
essentially this okay so how do you
write that down in general well G of
zero the orientation is
given I think some of us remember it
from last
week by those
vectors yeah
some of us might be wondering what does
t mean those vectors I mean this looks
like a single Vector not many vectors
but it is an illusion this is an M by m
Matrix and this is an M by m zero Matrix
so what I mean by those vectors is that
you look at The Columns of this
representation and you have the First
Column which is the first column of e
followed by 00 second column of e
followed by 0000 in other words it is
simply equal to E1 Follow by 0 0 E2
Follow by 0 0 and so on okay that is the
orientation basis for gamma zero the
orientation basis for gamma V you have
already guessed I hope is that
e up and then down you have the
derivative applied to e that's what it
is exactly as in the case of the fixed
Point theorem fix Point Theory and Fin
the orientation basis for the ambient
space in our case it is tangent bundle
is as usual e0 Follow by 0 e again I'd
like to emphasize that this zero is an M
bym Matrix not just a scal
zero okay so those are the
orientation basis for the main
characters in the
drama and at each of the equilibria that
is at each intersection point of the
zero section and the graph of the vector
field so
this
equilibrium the vector field B has index
plus or minus one as we
saw accordingly as
what the joint distribution of gamma 0
and Gamma V that is you take those two
things and put together form an enormous
Matrix 2 m by 2 m Matrix look at this
determinant and then you take this
that's also a 2m by 2m Matrix look at
this determinant if those determinants
have the same sign then the orientations
match if the determinant have the
opposite signs plus or minus one then
they have the opp opposite orientations
so um we have to look at the determinant
of
e0 and e v
Prime e but what is this well so this
part is the orientation basis for GMA
V and the other part
this bit is the orientation basis for
gamma of Z the zero section okay now
what is this it is equal to the
calculation is exactly the same as last
weeks it turns out to be the determinant
of e s whatever that is times the
determinant of B Prime over X that
yobi that's the one determinant we have
to worry about and the other determinant
which comes from there is the determin
of e 0 0 e and that's very very easy to
write down it's the determinant of e
s okay so the sentence is that the
vector field has index plus or minus one
that is the orientation match or
mismatch accordingly as those
determinants two determinants have the
same or the opposite
sides or the opposite SIDS
okay
therefore we can say the following you
see determinant V squ that's of course
positive what can make the sign the same
or differ exactly this determinant of B
Prime determinant of the akobian so you
get plus or minus depending on this is
plus or minus but but that's exactly
what we are claiming we're claiming the
index is the sign of this particular
determinant and so this finishes the
proof of the formula formula 8 is now
proed good in case you have fallen
asleep I don't blame you it's a time to
wake up the proof is a very nice
application of linear algebra this is
how you use for example the calculation
of determinant but in itself it's not
that important what is more important is
the following set of examples the
develop your
intuition let's use the formula now in
the next uh few minutes remain in order
to have a feel for what the index really
is and how to use that formula um in
practice so far we have been mostly
discussing onedimensional examples and
onedimensional examples although they
are of course
the basic and you should understand them
they tend to be sometimes too simple and
mislead us let's do
then 2D on R2 consider the following
Vector Fields Vector field x y and we
are going to first consider the case
where at each point XY you have the
vector whose components are X and Y I
hope you not confused by this
notation okay second we
shall look at the case when this is
equal to Min - x and minus y that's the
second Vector field and third case the
vector field where at X and Y you get
the values Min - x and
y and
fourth Vector
field can you see from the back if I
write this
small I think you have lot you have very
good eyesight so can you see in fact I
cannot my eyesight is so bad I cannot
even see who's sitting there oh hello
hello for example can you see what what
I'm writing there okay you have very
good eyes I
can't so Min - y and x and finally let's
look at the case of bxy where Y and - x
now why am I doing all this because I
want to do an exercise with
you what does the first Vector field
look like this let's figure it
out okay this is the
origin at the point0 what is the
vector zero so it doesn't move at origin
so it's an
equilibrium let's
now
think that's the origin please remember
that's a zero
point if I'm at this point and I want to
draw a vector here well I can draw a
vector this way this way this way this
way this way this way but one of those
vectors is the correct vector or at this
point which way does the vector Point
can you indicate with your
hand this
way
why can you explain
briefly at this point you're supp to
supposed to draw the vector whose
components are X and
Y okay so let's let's imagine that this
is the origin let's say that this point
is the point say whose coordinates are
what would be the coordinates of let's
try again what would be the coordinates
of this point just give some reasonable
coordinates one one one one so what is
the vector at this
Point look look at the point one one the
vector is supposed to look like this so
what are the components of the vector at
this
point Come On Come On yes you think it's
obvious and therefore you think it's
wrong but usually mathematics what's
obvious is what's right so please tell
me at this point what's the
vector let's call out the let's name the
components first at the point1 one what
is the what's the vector at that
point it's not one because there are two
numbers it cannot be one you have to
call two numbers what's the what are
components again one one one good so
what does the one one vector look
like straight up okay come to the
black please the vector whose components
are one and
one one and
one X component is one and Y component
is
one
okay let's erase
if you have a vector like this yeah what
are its
components let's say this length is one
and it's straight horizontal what are it
components one zero so it's not one one
so what's one
one what's one one what does the vector
one one look like
okay please step aside so that you can
show people step aside step on this side
so everyone can see
so tries this for the vector one one one
so I'd like to ask you then consider a
vector like this and this length is one
it's straight up what are it
components please write down
it goes straight up it doesn't go
anywhere
sideways so what are it
components ah but you said earlier that
this Vector is 01 one
Z is that your last word you're asking
me or am I asking
you do you think that's the those are
the components of that Vector that go
straight up by one
huh yes is that your answer you keep
looking at me and saying ah maybe Tashi
is going to say it's wrong and so I'm
going to change my mind and maybe if he
moves his nose a little bit I'm going to
change this and is this your answer okay
so so you said that um this has
components one one but that's not that's
not right
do you remember one minute ago you said
that this had this Vector was one one
was this Vector but that's not right
this Vector is 01 so what finally what
is the vector
one that's the X component that's the Y
component
I'll make it less confusing for you can
you draw the vector 2
three yeah X component is two and Y
component is three as usual
yeah can you draw an arrow to show what
it
is
flesh this is the point and then you
draw an arrow like this have you ever
seen this before no oh maybe you haven't
okay so that's how you draw the arrow
okay now question what is one
one okay so thank you very much that's
the vector one one you can go back thank
you we can upload her efforts so i' like
to ask if I'm here which way is the
vector pointing
that's the point 1
one at the point 1 one 1 x = 1 y = 1 the
vector must be one and one so which way
is the vector pointing can you show with
your
hand that way not this way not this way
that way because one one means you go
one in the positive X Direction and one
in the negative X positive y direction
so together you go in that direction if
you were 2 three h you go go two in the
X Direction and three in the y direction
that means that you go that way a little
higher if it's Min -2 and three what
does that mean you go minus 2 in the X
direction that means you go this way and
three in this way so you go that way and
so on clear good so at this stage at
this point you have to draw a vector
like this how about here anybody now
it's open for everyone
s really can which way does the vector
point at this
point think again at this
point so okay what are the coordinates
of this
point think
again okay so which way is the vector
point so which way is that Vector one Z
point does it Point straight up okay
come over
here come come over
here can you draw this Vector one
Z over here over one
Z One Z means that you go one in the X
Direction and zero in the y direction
yes so what's the
vector okay you look at me as if to say
ah am I doing the right thing am I
guessing right is this your answer
suppose that you have to bet 10,000
round on this answer would you bet it
yes you would yes because you're
courageous man go back so at this point
which way is the vector
pointing huh this
way okay
I hope by now all the class all the
class see understands what I mean we
should get going faster
yeah okay so at this point it's like
this and you can guess what's going to
happen this is the picture of the vector
field okay all right now what is the um
index of this a equilibrium there's an
equilibrium in the middle at the point0
what is that well in order to calculate
that equilibrium we have to calculate
the determinant of the yakobian so
what's the
yoban 0 01 1 0 0 1 Let's revise what the
determinant is really what we are doing
is to take the first component and
differentiating with respect to X
differentiate with respect to y you take
the second component differentiate with
respect to X and differentiate with
respect to Y most of you don't need to
be reminded of this but it is good to do
know so and then you have to calculate
the determinant and then see what the
sign is well this is very easy because
it's X differentiated with respect X
it's One X differentiated with respect
to Y it's zero and 0 one so as somebody
said that's the answer so that's what's
the thiser it's plus one which is
positive yeah so the index of this
Vector
field at this equilibrium is
positive okay so as we saw this is what
is called a
source and the source has index one
that's good news how about the next
example let's study
this let's do something again
are
you with me yet you are still writing um
aam has stopped writing so at this at
this point do do you see where I'm
pointing at this point yeah which way is
the vector
pointing here
like this like this yes so what are the
co components at this point according to
you- one one- one one so what is the
vector attached at this
point at a point - one one what's the
vector one one one one - one so which
way is the vector point
in 1 - one
which way is the vector
pointing you said that
way which
way 1 - one you go in the X Direction by
one y direction minus one which
direction is this you can draw if you
like but let's go fast
this this direction yes you go one in
the X Direction and minus one in the One
Direction that keep goes you puts you up
really minus one in the y direction and
that makes you climb the climb
up you do you agree with me I hope that
we have all memory that is we can keep
for about a few seconds so you are to
trying to draw 1 - one
yes which way does this Vector
Point huh s which way does this
point this way yes of course that
way so it's pointing this way and you
can see what's going to happen this is
the vector field
all of this is in fact amazingly
obvious look this Vector field is saying
that wherever you are yes this point
let's say is a point whose coordinates
are X and Y we are being asked to put
the vector whose components are X Y also
which means that you see this radius
Vector as the classical is is exactly
the vector that you put in there
at this point exactly a vector like this
exactly Vector like this in this case
it's the vector opposite to pointing in
the other direction to the radius Vector
so at this point you have to travel this
much in order to get to this point I
just point down Point towards the origin
you just come back that's what the
vector says vector field says so that's
what it is now what's the determinant of
the yoban in this case what huh- one 0 0
- one you can see that's curiously not
minus one but + one again so that's
positive so the index of
this
sync is + one again unlik in the
onedimensional
case I mention that in dimension M the S
has the index minus one to where did it
go I can't see it again oh- one to the
power Dimension B okay let's do this
then that's interesting at this point
which way does the vector
point in which direction is the vector
directed Z can you see at this
point correct good we are getting used
to this how about at this point of
view yeah it's going this way okay
that's interesting so
maybe it's like a sync however Amos at
this point which way that's the vector
point What's the value of the vector
field at this
point so say yeah so it goes
up so it's not a sync how about here one
more time
in down so do you see what's happening
along the X Direction it's coming in but
along the y direction it's going out so
I'd like to
ask somebody else H at this point let's
say the coordinates are one and one X is
one y is one which way does the vector
Field Point at
this
location exactly so this way so in fact
what's happening is that you get
the a Behavior like
this do you see so along the X Direction
I'm coming in being compressed this way
but along the the y direction I'm going
out so that you get this kind of
behavior this kind of
behavior this kind of behavior and this
kind of behavior and the origin does not
move this kind of thing this kind of
point is called a saddle point yeah do
you know what the saddle is
yes or no yes yeah but do you know what
the sadow really is originally when you
are riding a horse
you sit on something like
this correctly in French cell that's a
sadle and it's called a saddle because
you know you want to feel comfortable on
this so you usually have I'm
exaggerating this shape but the shape
like this it goes this way um along the
length of the horse but this way along
the um Direction perpendicular of the
horse that's why it's called sadle but
anyway that's a sadle and what is the
yoban in this case what are the entries
minus 1 0 0 1 now for the first time in
our discussion this becomes minus one
it's negative so the
index is -
one yeah so Saddles have negative index
whereas sour in dimension two have
positive index how about this let's then
finish the
job what do you think this Vector field
looks
like huh where does the vector Field
Point at this point for
example huh here
somebody take the
initiative up thank you and
here left and so on have you SE have we
seen this Vector field before yes we
have so we shouldn't really spend five
minutes doing this it's of course the
vector field that you all know is the
rotation Vector field but rotation in
One
Direction in a direction that we call
anticlockwise or counterclockwise in
America so here the yakobian is what 0 -
one 1 0 what is this determinant
please somebody said minus one one plus
one so that's positive and therefore the
index is + one by the way I would like
to make a little issue a warning you
know all those determinants came out be
plus one or minus one and IND this is
therefore become plus orus one you
should realize that determinants don't
always come out to be plus or minus one
they can be plus 20 or-35 and so on but
I'm saying this is plus index is plus
one because the determinant is positive
that's the only thing that I care about
okay for example in this case instead of
Min - Y and and X suppose that I got - 2
Y and +
3x yeah it's going to modify the picture
but the determinant is going to be
determinant of 0 - 2 and 3 0 and that's
going to be + 6 that's positive so the
index is still one index is not six okay
we only care about the sign of the
determinant and that gives you plus or
minus index okay how about this
finally what do you think this is a
quick job is to look at the previous
example and notice that it's netive of
the previous example so what do we do
well the previous example was rotating
anticlockwise here you have to rotate
clockwise that's all there is good you
see if we do mathematics this way we can
accomplish a lot and you know in a few
years you can even get the
PHD okay so this is what it is and here
the calculation is again easy
determinant of 0 1 - 1 0 and
interestingly that's again 1 + 1 POS
positive so the index of this sitation
is again + one this is the anticlockwise
or count counterclockwise
rotation and this is clockwise
rotation for some reason mathematicians
decided for a long time ago that
clockwise is negative rotation and
anticlockwise is positive rotation maybe
mathematicians like to go to the Past
rather than to the future I don't know
why it's different from the this kind of
convention okay I hope that that calcul
those
calculations may make it clear how we
use that
formula as we said however in the
beginning of this discussion we will not
make much use of this formula you might
use this formula when you apply the
theory in your future work but as far as
we're concerned it's much more important
to understand the picture of what we are
doing and just with the conceptual
understanding of the picture we can
deduce a lot of interesting
applications okay that's enough